<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db_errors>
  <!-- Oracle errors -->
    <error>
        <number>ORA-00937</number>
        <title>: not a single-group group function</title>
        <user_message>  A SELECT list cannot include both a group function, such
        as AVG, COUNT, MAX, MIN, SUM, STDDEV, or VARIANCE, and an individual column
        expression, unless the individual column expression is included in a GROUP
        BY clause.  If this did not help you or did not cause this error or you have
        any questions please contact us using the link below.</user_message>
    </error>
    <error>
        <number>ORA-00979</number>
        <title>not a GROUP BY expression</title>
        <user_message>  The GROUP BY clause does not contain all the expressions in
        the SELECT clause. SELECT expressions that are not included in a group
        function, such as AVG, COUNT, MAX, MIN, SUM, STDDEV, or VARIANCE, must be
        listed in the GROUP BY clause.  If this did not help you or did not
        cause this error or you have any questions please contact us using the link
        below.</user_message>
    </error>
    <error>
        <number>ORA-01722</number>
        <title>invalid number</title>
        <user_message>  The attempted conversion of a character string to a number
        failed because the character string was not a valid numeric literal. Only
        numeric fields or character fields containing numeric data may be used in
        arithmetic functions or expressions. Only numeric fields may be added to or
        subtracted from dates.  If this did not help you or did not
        cause this error or you have any questions please contact us using the link
        below.</user_message>
    </error>
    <error>
        <number>ORA-01791</number>
        <title>not a SELECTed expression</title>
        <user_message>  This error occurs when a query is built that sorts on a
        field that is not selected for output and also contains the SQL directive
        "DISTINCT."  In order to retrieve your data, use your browser's back
        button and either make sure you have selected for output all the fields you
        are sorting on, or check the box in the output selections that reads
        "Include duplicate rows in returned data ."  Note this will cause you to
        get duplicate data if you have mulitple, identical rows.  If this did not
        cause this error or you have any questions please contact us using the link
        below.</user_message>
    </error>
    <error>
        <number>ORA-01858</number>
        <title>: a non-numeric character was found where a numeric was expected</title>
        <user_message>  The input data to be converted using a date format model
        was incorrect. The input data did not contain a number where a number was
        required by the format model.  If this did not help you or did not
        cause this error or you have any questions please contact us using the link
        below.</user_message>
    </error>
    <error>
        <number>ORA-00932</number>
        <title>: Oracle does not allow SELECT DISTINCT with a CLOB data type</title>
        <user_message>This error occurs when a user has the SQL directive
        "DISTINCT." on a query containing a CLOB or XMLCLOB datatype column as output.
        In order to retrieve your data, use your browser's back
        button and check the box in the output selections that reads
        "Include duplicate rows in returned data ."  Note this will cause you to
        get duplicate data if you have mulitple, identical rows.  If this did not
        cause this error or you have any questions please contact us using the link
        below.
	</user_message>
    </error>
  <!-- /Oracle errors -->
    <error>  <!-- Postgres duplicate primary key message -->
        <number>ERROR: duplicate key violates unique constraint</number>
        <title>Duplicate data item entered.</title>
        <user_message>This error occurs when an attempt is made to re-enter data
        that has already be entered in the database.  Required data cannot usually 
        be listed in a database more than once.  Check the database to determine 
        if the data you are trying to enter is already there.</user_message>
    </error>
</db_errors>
